Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
R. Freeman Butts papers
1923-2004
80114
Hoover Institution Archives
399 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope, 16 slide boxes, 1 sound cassette (168.2 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, studies, conference papers and proceedings, syllabi, curricular material, clippings, and other printed matter relating to the role of education in society, civic education, education in the United States, and international education.
Butts, R. Freeman (Robert Freeman), 1910-
Access
Collection open for research. Boxes are stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, with a substantial increment added later.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1910 May 14 Born, Springfield, Illinois
1931 Awarded bachelor of arts degree, University of Wisconsin
1935 Awarded doctorate, University of Wisconscin
1948-1975 Professor, Teachers College, Columbia University
1973 Author, The Education of the West
1978 Author, Public Education in the United States: From Revolution to Reform
1989 Author, The Civic Mission in Educational Reform: Perspectives for the Public and the Profession
1993 Author, In the First Person Singular: The Foundations of Education
2010 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The R. Freeman Butts collection contains writings, research materials, correspondence, and other materials relating to a prominent American educator. A prolific author, Butts wrote a number of books and contributed numerous articles to professional journals in the field of education. Butts wrote extensively on themes of public education and citizenship; he wrote critically about efforts to privatize education and create charter schools. He also participated in numerous professional organizations, and the collection contains correspondence, minutes of meetings, and reports relating to these activities. Additionally, the collection contains biographical materials, including student papers and photographs.
Civics--Study and teaching.; Education--United States.; International education.
- GENERAL
  - Intercultural education materials, (1940s) (Box 1)
  - Educational Foundations materials (Ed. 200 Fb)
  - Intercultural education, (1940s) (Box 2)
  - Intercultural education - New Rochelle Workshop (Box 3)
  - Educational Foundations materials (Ed. 200 Fa)
    - Education and Culture
    - American Democracy Faces the Future
    - Economics and Democracy
    - Democracy and Political Power
  - Ed. 200 Fa materials, (1940s and 1950s) (Box 4)
    - Democracy and Stable World Order
    - Intergroup Relations
    - Social Role of Education in the World Today
  - Ed. 200 Fa materials - American Education and World War II (Box 5)
  - Ed. 200 Fa materials, (1930s) (Box 6)
  - Instructional materials on (Box 7)
    - History of Western Education
    - Intellectual History of Education
  - Frontiers of Democracy, (1939-1942)
  - Ed. 200 Fa - Religion and Education, (1950s) (Box 8)
  - Ed. 200 Fa - Religion, States Rights, Desegregation, (1950s) (Box 9)
  - Letter from MacIver - Madison
  - Ed 200 Fa (Box 10)
    - Desegregation, Freedom
    - Excellence in the Curriculum
  - Ed. 200 Fb - Curriculum, Educational Program, Knowledge (Box 11)
  - Soft pedagogy - Bestor, et. al., (1957)
  - New Conservatism, (1958)
  - New Lincoln School Conference - Gould House, (1958)
  - Tamiment Institute Conference, (1958)
    - Papers by Childs, Bestor, Hook
    - Note to RFB by Polykaup Husch: "Three Cheers for T.C."
  - Ed. 200Fb - Humanism, Intellectualism, Catholicism, (1940) (Box 12)
  - Abstract of Ph.D. Thesis at Wisconsin on Elective System by RFB
  - Correspondence, (1944-46)
  - Article for Encyclopedia of Modern Education, (1942)
  - Article for Educational Record on "International Perspective on the Role of Liberal Arts and Professional Education in the Preparation of Teachers", (1957)
  - All-College Lecture on Church and State, (1951)
  - Article for Project on Cooperative Development of Public School Administration - Dan Davies - "The Setting, the Job, the Man", (1953) (Box 13)
  - Reviews and correspondence about A Cultural History of Education, (1947)
  - Correspondence on The College Charts Its Course, (1939)
  - "Freedom and Responsibility in American Education, (1952-5) (Box 14)
  - "Arnold Toynbee's Philisophy of History", (1952)
  - "Persistent Issues in High School Education" - Purdue Conference, (1952)
  - Revision of " A Cultural History of Western Education ", (1955)
  - "To the Veteran on the College Campus" in Teachers College Record, (1945?)
  - "Historical and Philosophical Foundations of Education," in Review of Educational Research, (1952)
  - Text for Coronet Films "History of American Education", (1958) (Box 15)
  - Cooperative Bureau of Teachers, (1946-49)
  - ETS - Graduate Record Exams in Education, (1953)
  - University of Wisconsin Centennial Conference on Higher Education - "Faculty Participation in Policy Formulation", (1948)
  - Speech at Hampton Institute, (1942) (Box 16)
  - Keuka Conference - Week of Work, (1941)
  - "Colonial Period in the History of American Education" (with E. H. Reisner) in Review of Educational Research
  - Correspondence, (1941-42)
  - Articles on Education for the Gifted, (1941)
  - Review of Curti and Carstenson, The University of Wisconsin
  - "Liberal Education and the Prescribed Curriculum" an article for the Journal of Higher Education and The Educational Record
  - Correspondence related to Wisconsin Disseration, (1932-34)
  - Visiting Professor, University of Wisconsin, (1949)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 17)
    - Meiklejohn, Wisconsin, Illinois, Berkeley, Brubacher
  - AASA Conventions s), (1950s-60
  - Conventions - AAUP, ACE, AERA, AHA, History of Education, Amer. Studies Assn., Assn. of Higher Education (1950s-1960s), (1955-57) (Box 18)
  - Assn. of Higher Education, (1957-58) (Box 19)
  - ASCD, (1956)
  - Correspondence with Carnegie Corp - Gardner, Stackpole, (1960s)
  - Cleveland Conference, (1957-59)
  - Comparative Education Society, (1957-60)
  - Committee for the Study of Mankind, (1960) (Box 20)
  - Fundamental Education, (1960)
  - Correspondence
    - Educational Forum
    - Educational Policies Commission, (1961)
    - Encyclopedia of Ed. Research
  - John Dewey
    - 90th birthday, (1949)
    - Centennial Conference (RFB Remanks), 1959
  - John Dewey Society, (1955-1960)
  - Educational T.V. Series (Phil Phenix), (1960)
  - Harpers
  - Journal of Teacher Ed., (1958-59) (Box 21)
  - Middle States Philosophy of Ed. Society
  - New Lincoln Centennial, (1958)
  - NCTEPS, (1959)
  - Philosophy of Ed. Society, (1954-56)
  - Review of Horace Kallen
  - Rockland County Day School - Charles Frankel
  - Salzburg Seminar, (1955)
  - Tamiment Seminar, (1958)
  - "History of Education" - Article for Brittanica, (1958)
  - Articles for World Book, (1957-58) (Box 22)
  - N.S.S.E. Yearbook on Education for the Professions
  - Correspondence in Paris, (1966)
  - Visit of Bernardino to T.C., (1965)
  - ACLU Church and State Committee
  - Xerox copies of Amherst Report, (1827)
  - Inauguration of T.C. President John Fischer, (1962)
  - Harold Benjamin National Memorial Fund
  - Butler Award
  - Correspondence with Brickman re: Brubacher
  - Correspondence filed under "C" (Box 23)
  - Caswell
  - Center for Research and Education in American Liberties, (1965-70)
  - Christmas letter to Overseas Staff
  - College of the Potomac - James Russell
  - Church and State Committee - ACLU
  - Columbia Crisis - folders turned over to Kenneth Toepfer at T.C.
  - Commencement escort for James Allen Robert Weaver (1966), John Brademas (1967), (1964)
  - Coombs, Philip
  - Cordier, Andrew
  - Counts, George
  - Cremen, Laurence
  - Correspondence "D" through "F" (Box 24)
  - "Democracy and Crisis" - T.C. Faculty Statement, (1940)
  - Dillon, Wilton
  - Dodge, Cleveland
  - Doob, Leonard
  - Education Bills, (1965)
  - ERIC
  - Fischer, John s), (1960s-70
  - Frankel, Charles - on Cultural Arrairs
  - Franklin Book Awards
  - Correspondence "G" to "K" (Box 25)
  - Gardner, John
  - Gates, Arthur - Memorial
  - Cohen, Wilbur
  - Howe, Harold
  - Leestura, Robert
  - International Programs at T.C.
  - Institute of International Ed.
  - Itineraries of international travel
  - Invitations to speak - mostly declined
  - Kappa Delta Pi - Laureate Chapter
  - Kandel, Isaac
  - Kilpatrick, W. H.
  - Correspondence "K" to "R" (Box 26)
  - Kirk, Grayson
  - McGill
  - McGovern Bill (on Education?)
  - Membership dues
  - Miel, Alice
  - Mukerji visit to T.C., (1972)
  - TEA Reception at T.C., (1963)
  - Nyerere speech to TEA at T.C., (1961)
  - Orata visit to T.C.
  - T.C. Chart of Internationl Studies
  - Peruvian delegation visit to T.C., (1963)
  - Pifer, Alan
  - Prakasha, Veda
  - Porter, Arthur
  - ICED
  - Quik and Capelle visits to T.C.
  - T.C. Reorganization, (1964)
  - Correspondence "S" to "T" (Box 27)
  - Schaefer, Robert
  - Shield (Masai)
  - Sirken of World Bank
  - Springer, Hugh - University of West Indies
  - Stiler, Lindley
  - Storage files at T.C.
  - Education and World Affairs Task Force
  - TEA Dinner, (1963)
  - Thailand visitors from Stanford, (1963)
  - Correspondence, Papers, and Conferences, (1960s) (Box 28)
  - Toepfer, Kenneth
  - Ward, Champion
  - Watson, Goodwin
  - Education in Bahamas
  - Bereday's Comparative Education Class, (1964)
  - Center for the Justice of International Studies, (1970)
  - Agriculture Deans Conference - Fort Collins Philosophy and Objective of Higher Education, (1960)
  - ACE, (1967, 1973)
  - AID, (1962)
  - ICED - Aspen Institute, (1973)
  - ATEA - materials sent to James Sheffield, (1975)
  - Longview Foundation
  - Joe Burnett on Foundations of Education and Toynbee
  - Center for Mass Communication
  - Center at Santa Barbara
  - International Education Art Conference at Cornell
  - Campus Coordinators
  - Introductions of Hogarth at T.C. Distinguished Lecture Series, (1963) (Box 29)
  - Dag Hammarskjold Conference at Denver, (1964)
  - ECS - Miami and IDEA (1974)
  - Educational Policies Commission, (1964)
  - Greystone Conference for Elementary and Secondary Principals, (1966)
  - IIE Conference - Washington, (1964)
  - Colloquium for William O. Stanley - Champaign, (1971)
  - Ford International Meetings, (1964)
  - Arden House Speech, (1974)
  - Indiana University - "A Teaching College for the World"
  - Indiana Seminar, (1970) (Box 30)
  - IBM Seminar
  - ICED
  - IEA - Hamburg; Lake Mohawk (1967), (1966)
  - Council for International Exchange of Persons, (1974)
  - International Schools Services, (1965-74)
  - IIE, (1969)
  - Home Economics Conference - Iowa State University: "Role of Universities in Human Resource Development", (1965)
  - Jamaica trip and proposed project with Ralph Fields, (1973) (Box 31)
  - Japanese teachers at T.C., (1965)
  - ICET Orientation group at T.C., (1967)
  - MSSC Conference, (1973)
  - African Book of Readings in Foundations of Education, (1973)
  - Memphis State University - Sam H. Johnson Lecture, (1973)
  - World Foundation Conference on Overseas Service Training Programs, (1963)
  - Meiklejohn Experimental College Reunion - Madison, (1962)
  - University of Nairobi - RFB as External Examiner, (1972)
  - Several conferences on international education: Princeton Conference on Quality in Education (1964); Nairobi; National Council of Churches; Foreign Policy; Pacem in Terris; Nebraska University; Niblett; Nigeria Radio; New Paltz; UNESCO; Ohio University; McGill; Pakistan Seminar; Peace Corps Symposium; Wingspread (Box 32)
  - International conferences: - Rutgers; Columbia School of International Affairs; Southern Illinois University (Oliver Caldwell and Robert Jacobs); Stetten Conference on Overseas Programs; Syracuse Conference on International Education Planners, (1963) (Box 33)
  - T.C. Non-Major Requirements, (1930s, 1940s, 1950s)
  - Studies in Philosophy of Education (Villemain)
  - T.C. Foundations Requirements, (1940s) (Box 34)
    - Education 200 Fa Syllabi, Quiz Questions, News clippings
    - Questions for Graduate Record Exam in Education
  - Education 200 Fa Materials: Problems of Democracy, Economy s), (1940s-50 (Box 35)
  - Education 200 Fa Materials: Politics and Democratic State, American Foreign Policy, (1950s) (Box 36)
  - Education 200 Fa Materials (Box 37)
    - World Society (Marshall Plan, Colonialism)
    - Intergroup Relations, (1950s)
  - Education 200 Fa - Intergroup Relations; Social Role of Education, (1950s) (Box 38)
  - Education 302 H - History of Higher Education s), (1950s-60
    - Brown University Catalog, (1850s)
  - Education 202 E - History of Western Education s), (1940s-50 (Box 39)
  - Education 202 E - History of Western Education s), (1940s-50 (Box 40)
  - Education 102 E - A Cultural History of Education, (1930s)
  - Notes from Kilpatrick Course at T.C.
  - Notes from Experimental College and philosophy courses at Wisconsin s), (1920s-30
  - Notes from history courses and history of education courses at Wisconsin and Columbia - Chase, Sellery, Lynn Thorndike, Otto (Box 41)
  - Education 200 F Syllabus - Brunner, Kaudel, Reisner
  - Education 201 E - History of Western Education, (1940s) (Box 42)
  - History of Educational Bibliographies - Reisner, Tewksbury, Chase
  - History of Education Course at Wisconsin, (1949) (Box 43)
  - History of Education Notes, (1930s)
  - Tewksbury's Course on Comparative Cultures
  - Education 200 Fb - Syllabus and materials - Roup, Benne, Butts, Dix, (1940s)
  - Philosophy of Education - Course outlines - Roup, Childs
  - Education 200 Fb - Watson, Butts
  - Role of Historical Foundations in the Professional Education of Teachers - Brickman, Crewin, Moehlwan, Chiapetta, Lee, Wootan, Butts, (1953)
  - Education 200 Fb - Watson, Davitz, Butts, (1956) (Box 44)
  - Education 200 Fb - Watson, Butts, (1957)
  - Education 200 Fb - Education and Human Nature, Communication, Adjustment, Intelligence and Learning, Art and Aesthetics, Role of the Profession, Social Class, Group Dynamics, etc. (Box 45)
  - RFB Speech on Art, Education, and Moral and Spiritual Values - Kutztown Teachers College, (1951)
  - Education 200 Fb Materials: Communication, Adjustive Behavior, Intelligence, Aesthetics, Moral and Religious Experience, Vocation (Box 46)
  - Gordon Lee - Introduction to Education Syllabus
  - Eggertsen syllabus in history of education at Michigan, (1947)
  - Education 200 F Syllabuses- (one marked Childs), 1934-35
  - Education 200 F Syllabi, (1935-42) (Box 47)
  - Reisner Syllabus on Intellectual and Ethical Backgrounds of Modern Education, (1935)
  - Education 200 F Syllabi, (1946-51) (Box 48)
  - Stanley, Smith, Anderson syllabus on Social Aspects of Education at University of Illinois, (1948)
  - Education 209M - syllabus on American Culture and Education for Foreign Students at T.C. - Clarence Lintan and Virginia French
  - Materials by RFB for courses on: (Box 49)
    - Education and the Modernization Process, (1972-73)
    - Comparative History of Higher Education, 1972)
    - Education of the West s), (1960s-70
  - Materials by RFB for courses on: (Box 50)
    - Education and the Modernization Process, (1960s)
    - History and Theory of Higher Education, (1960s)
  - Materials for RFB for courses on: (Box 51)
    - Foundations of Education and History of Education, (1950s)
  - Materials for RFB for courses on: (Box 52)
    - Foundations of Education and History of Education and Church and State, (1950s)
  - Materials for RFB for courses on: (Box 53)
    - Foundations of Education and History of Education and Church and State, (1950s)
  - Bound books - Readings in the Foundations of Education. Volumes I and II (Box 54)
  - Notes by RFB taken as a graduate student at Wisconsin in courses by Chase, Willing, History of German People, (1930s) (Box 55)
  - Paper by RFB for Max Otto on William James, (1933 or 1934)
  - Materials for courses in History of Education at T.C.
  - Education 200 F Syllabus, (1935)
  - RFB Paper on Dewey for Chase at Wisconsin, (1933?) (Box 56)
  - RFB Notes on Course by Jowlkes at Wisconsin, (1932)
  - Materials for courses on history of education at T.C.
  - Materials for courses at T.C. during World War II (Box 57)
  - RFB proposals for a course on Education in War and Post-War Times at T.C., (1942)
  - Progressive Education and the Experiment of the 30 Schools - article by John Bergstressor on Evaluation, (1937)
  - Progressive Education - Philosophy as seen at Wisconsin and T.C. s), (1930s-40 (Box 58)
  - RFB courses on School and Society and History of Education at Wisconsin, (1949)
  - Education 302H materials - History of Higher Education, (1937-1960) (Box 59)
  - "Basic Features of American Education," a chapter for Bereday's editing of an Italian Journal, (1956)
  - "General View of American Higher Education" for Columbia University Student Council and John Hay Whitney Seminar, (1956)
  - "The Power of Education" High School Commencement Speech by RFB: "3S's in Success", (1956)
  - "The Year 1956" - article for School Executive
  - Education 302H - History of Higher Education Materials (Box 60)
  - Liberal Education publications from Earl McGrath's Institute
  - ACE Meeting, (1957)
  - Education 202E - History of Western Education Notes
  - Education 302H History of Higher Education Materials, (1941) (Box 61)
  - RFB Articles and book reviews on higher education (published and unpublished) Recent currents of though in American Colleges; Historic Controversies in Educational Philosophy (Keuka Conference); Education of the Gifted; Veterans; Hampton Institute; Chapter with Tewksbury for Liberal Education in Our Times, (1960s)
  - International Education; Yearbook of Educational editorial board ff.), (1961
  - T.C. Committee on International Education to Board of Trustees, (1956-57)
  - T.C. Committee on International Education to Board of Trustees, (1956-57) (Box 62)
  - Proposals for International Institute at T.C. with Jim Russell ff.), (1955
  - Akrawi's speech at Caswell's Inauguration, (1955)
  - ACE Committee on Institutional Projects Abroad, (1956)
  - Materials on Academic Freedom (late early 1950s) Communist teachers; attacks on schools; censorship of texts, 1940s- (Box 63)
  - ACLU - Academic Freedom Committee, (1950s) (Box 64)
  - ACLU - Church and State Committee, (1950s)
  - Citizenship Education Project at T.C. ff.), (1949 (Box 65)
  - Proposal for a Program on Human Relations at T.C., (1947)
  - ACE Commission on Teacher Education: Conference on Evaluation at Columbus, (1942)
  - ACE Commission on Teacher Education - Workshop - Chicago, (1940) (Box 66)
  - ACE Commission on Teacher Education - Workshop - Ithaca, (1940)
  - ACE Commission on Teacher Education - Workshop - Highland Park, (1941)
  - Report on Visit to Southern Schools and Colleges - Henry Sunar, Arthur Bestor, Tewksbury, RFB
  - Pre-Service Programs at T.C., Columbia (Box 67)
    - Reports of progress (early, 1940s)
    - Evenden - Butts book
  - Pre-Service Program Reports (Box 68)
  - Materials used in Education 51ES - Seminar for Columbia and Barnard Undergraduates
  - Education 51ES - as taught "Life Histories", (1940-45) (Box 69)
  - Education 01A as taught, (1936-39) (Box 70)
  - "Around the World in 30 Days", (1969)
  - RFB Fulbright Award to Australia, (1954)
  - RFB Personal - Much could be removed (Box 71)
  - RFB "Glowing Letters"
  - Biodata - W.H. Kilpatrick Award (Box 72)
  - Permission for reprinting RFB articles:
    - "Search for Freedom" NEA, (1960)
    - "American Education in International Development", (1963)
    - "Professor Butts in the News"
  - RFB Magazine articles (Box 73)
  - Publishers' correspondence and contracts: Harpers, Holt, Beacon, McGraw-Hill, Encyclopedia Brittanica, World Book, Encyclopedia of Education
  - Carnegie Travel Grant, (1961-62)
  - Publicity about RFB books: American Education in International Development (Box 74)
  - Articles by RFB: New York Times Supplement on "Education in India"
  - "Mission of the Educationary", (1966)
  - "Civilization as Historical Process"
  - RFB reviews of books by Max Rafferty Paul Nash, Richard Storr, (1964)
  - Articles and speeches - History of Education Society on "Civilization Building"; "Civilization on Historical Process", (1966) (Box 75)
  - N.S.S.E. Yearbook articles by Shane and RFB
  - Kansas TEPS Conference "If I Had My Way", (1959)
  - The Foundations of Educational Idea - Working notes of the T.C. Departmental Seminar, (1950s)
  - Education 200F Materials on Education and the Intellectual Life, Segregation, the Profession, (1950s) (Box 76)
  - Education 200F - Materials on International affairs, Basic Characteristics of American Education, Education and Religion, Academic Freedom, (1950s) (Box 77)
  - Education 200F - Materials on International and Comparative Education, Politics, Knowledge and Curriculum (Box 78)
  - The Foundations of Educational Idea - Working notes of the T.C. Departmental Seminar, (1950s)
  - Education 200F Materials on Education and the Intellectual Life, Segregation, the Profession, (1950s) (Box 76)
  - Education 200F - Materials on International affairs, Basic Characteristics of American Education, Education and Religion, Academic Freedom, (1950s) (Box 77)
  - Education 200F - Materials on International and Comparative Education, Politics, Knowledge and Curriculum (Box 78)
  - Maryland Survey by RFB, (1959)
  - Education 200F - Materials on Teacher Education; Academic Freedom (Box 79)
  - The Foundations of Education Idea - Working Notes and drafts
  - Materials on Religion, Profession, Teacher Education (Box 80)
  - African Studies Association
  - Associations: African Studies Association; AAUP; HES; Asia Society; ACE (International Education); AERA; AHA; AAHE; AHE (Box 81)
  - Associations: AHE; AHA; AIR; Comparative Administration Group, (1966) (Box 82)
  - Associations: Cleveland Conference; Committee on the Future of International Studies ff.); CIES (1974 ff.), (1971 (Box 83)
  - Associations: CIES; Consortium for International Studies Education, (1960s) (Box 84)
  - Associations: John Dewey Society; HES (1960s); Horace Mann League (Box 85)
  - RFB John Dewey Lecture, (1963)
  - "Education for New Nationhood" - RFB Lecture in Kabul
  - Associations: ICET; International Schools Foundation; International Studies Association (Box 86)
  - Kappa Delta Pi Laureate Chapter
  - Maryland Survey
  - RFB Correspondence: H to M; N-Z (1966-67); A to G (1969-70); H to M (1969-70) (Box 87)
  - RFB Correspondence: N to Z, (1969-70) (Box 88)
  - Revision of A Cultural History to Education of the West, (1970s)
  - East-West Center Senior Specialist: Materials
  - East-West Center Senior Specialist (1965) Materials, correspondence, prospectus for research on Education of the West (Box 89)
  - RFB Correspondence while at East-West Center, (1965) (Box 90)
  - TEEA and TEA materials, (1960s)